Guide to the Max Walter Commercial Art for W. & J. Sloane
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Max Walter commercial art for W. & J. Sloane
1934-1981
GEN MSS 929
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
5.33
(15 boxes)
The collection consists primarily of pen-and-wash drawings of furniture and home accessories drawn by Max Walter for the W. & J. Sloane company. The drawings depict a range of furniture and home furnishing styles available to the public and were featured in advertisements for W. & J. Sloane printed in newspapers and magazine. The drawings document changing styles in the American commercial domestic furniture industry in the middle decades of the twentieth century. Also found are sketchbooks containing pastel, watercolor, pencil, and pen-and-wash drawings and copies of print advertisements featuring Walter's drawings.
Walter, Max, 1908-1988
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Rachelle S. Blaxberg on the Library Associates Endowment Fund, 2012.
Custodial History
From the collection of Jack Lubiner.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Max Walter (1908-1988)
Max Walter, American illustrator, studied at the Arts Students League of New York (1925-1926), and drew illustrations of furniture and home accessories for the W. & J. Sloane company for more than 35 years during the middle decades of the twentieth century.
W. & J. Sloane
W. & J. Sloane was a furniture and rug store in New York City that catered to the wealthy and operated from 1843 to 1985, reaching its peak in the late nineteenth and early twentieth centuries.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists primarily of pen-and-wash drawings of furniture and home accessories drawn by Max Walter for the W. & J. Sloane company. The drawings depict a range of furniture and home furnishing styles available to the public and were featured in advertisements for W. & J. Sloane printed in newspapers and magazines. The drawings document changing styles in the American commercial domestic furniture industry in the middle decades of the twentieth century. Also found are sketchbooks containing pastel, watercolor, pencil, and pen-and-wash drawings and copies of print advertisements featuring Walter's drawings.
Arrangement
Organized into three series by format: I. Pen-and-Wash Drawings, 1934-1981. II. Sketchbooks, 1951-1952. III. Advertisements, undated.
Advertising -- United States; Commercial art -- United States; Commercial artists -- United States; House furnishings -- United States; House furnishings industry and trade -- United States; Furniture -- United States; Furniture industry and trade -- United States; Illustrators -- United States; Advertisements -- United States -- 20th Century; Commercial art -- United States -- 20th Century; Pen and wash drawings -- United States -- 20th Century; Sketchbooks -- United States -- 20th Century; Illustrators -- United States -- 20th Century; Commercial artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Walter, Max, 1908-1988; W. & J. Sloane; Lubiner, Jack -- Ownership
- Pen-and-Wash Drawings, 1934-1981; Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged by size and then by date.
  - Pen-and-wash drawings (8.5" x 14" or smaller)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1934-1946; 13 (Box 1)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1946-1954; 8 (Box 2)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1955-1959; 5 (Box 3)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1960-1978; 16 (Box 4)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings
      - Bedding, bedroom, undated (Box 5)
      - Chairs, undated (Box 5)
      - Dining sets, undated (Box 5)
      - End tables, undated (Box 5)
      - Kitchen accessories, undated (Box 5)
      - Law furniture, undated (Box 5)
      - Lighting, undated (Box 5)
      - Living room, undated (Box 5)
      - Miscellaneous: mirror, foyer, receptacles, towels, undated (Box 5)
      - Planters, umdated (Box 5)
      - Trays, tables, undated (Box 5)
      - Window curtains, undated (Box 5)
      - Writing desks, undated (Box 5)
  - Pen-and-wash drawings (14" x 18" or smaller)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1935-1949, undated; 16 (Box 6 (Oversize))
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1950-1956; 10 (Box 7 (Oversize))
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1957-1964; 9 (Box 8 (Oversize))
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1965-1977; 14 (Box 9 (Oversize))
  - Pen-and-wash drawings (16" x 20" or smaller)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1940-1959, undated; 15 (Box 10 (Oversize))
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1960-1981; 18 (Box 11 (Oversize))
  - Pen-and-wash drawings (22" x 28" or smaller)
    - Pen-and-wash drawings, 1968, undated (Box 12 (Oversize))
- Sketchbooks, 1951-1952, undated; Series II
  - Pastel drawings on construction paper, undated; 2 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - Watercolor drawings, 1951 (Box 13 (Oversize))
  - Watercolor, pencil, and pen-and-wash drawings, December 1951-January 1952 (Box 13 (Oversize))
- Advertisements, undated; Series III
  - Advertisements (copies), undated; 2 (Box 14 (Oversize))
  - Advertisements (copies), undated; 31 (Box 15)